the whole Spinoza
was a 17th century Dutch philosopher who
tried to reinvent
religion moving it away from something
based on superstition
and ideas have direct divine
intervention to being a discipline
that was going to be far more impersonal
Quays I scientific
and yet also at times serenely consoling
the whole the word means blessed in
hebrew
was born in the Jewish quarter Amsterdam
in 1632
a thriving central Jewish commerce in
thought his ancestors were sephardic
jews
who'd fled the Spanish Peninsula
following the Catholic conspired
expulsion in 1492
the whole house studios highly
intelligent child received an intense
the traditional Jewish education
he went to the local church school the
issue for and followed all the Jewish
High Holidays and rituals
the gradually he began to distance
himself from the fate of his ancestors
although I have been educated from
boyhood in the accepted beliefs
concerning scripture
he later wrote with characteristic
caution I felt bound
in the end to embrace of the views is
fully fleshed-out views
would be expressed his great work the
ethics written entirely in Latin
and published in 1677 in the ethics
Spinoza directly challenge the main
tenets have two days in particular
and organized religion in general God is
not a person who stands outside of
nature
there is no one to hear our prayers or
to create miracles
or to punish us for misdeeds the is no
afterlife
man is not God's chosen creature the
Bible was only written by
ordinary people got is not craftsman or
an architect in or easy a
King more military strategist to calls
for believers to take up the Holy sold
God doesn't see anything notice expect
anything
he doesn't charge he doesn't even reward
the virtuous with the life after death
every representation of court as a
person is a projection of the
imagination
and everything in the traditional
liturgical calendar is pure superstition
and mumbo-jumbo
however despite all this remarkably
Spinoza did not declare himself an
atheist
he insisted that he remained a staunch
defender of gold
go to place an absolutely central role
in Spinoza's ethics
but it isn't anything like the gold who
wants a pages of the Old Testament
Spinoza's gordy's holy impersonal and
indistinguishable from what we might
variously called
nature or existence or a world soul
gorgeous the universe and its laws
gold is reason and truth gold is the
animating force in
everything that is and can be he is not
in time
and he cannot be individual eated
Spinoza rights
whatever he is is in gold and nothing
can exist will be conceived without got
throughout his text Spinoza was keen to
undermine the idea of
prayer in prayer an individual appeals
to God
to change the way the universe works but
spinners
argues that this is entirely the wrong
way around the task of human beings
is to try to understand how and why the
universe works the way it does
and then accept it rather than protest
at the workings existence
by sending little messages up into the
sky Espinosa put it beautifully but
rather coarse thickly
who so ever love scored cannot strive
that cord
should love him in return in other words
only it deeply distorted and
infantile narcissism would lead someone
that wants to believe in court
and then to imagine that this Court
would take an interest in bending the
rules have existence
to improve his or her life in some way
Spinoza was deeply influenced by the
philosophy of the Stoics have ancient
Greece and Rome
they had argued the wisdom lies not in
protest against how things are
but in continuous attempts to understand
the ways of the world
and then power down peacefully to
necessity Seneca
spinners as favorite philosopher had
compared human beings two dogs on a
leash
being led by the necessities of life in
a range of directions
the movement pools against what's
necessary the mall one is strangled
and therefore the wise must always
endeavor try to understand ahead of time
how things are
for example what love is like oh how
politics works
and then change the direction
accordingly so as not to be strangled
unnecessarily
it is this kind of stoic attitude the
constantly pervades Spinoza's philosophy
to understand God traditionally means
studying the Bible in other holy text
but Spinoza now introduces another idea
the best way to New called
is to understand how life and the
universe work it through knowledge of
psychology philosophy in the natural
sciences
the one comes to understand got in
traditional religion
believers ask special favors I've got
Spinoza proposes instead
that we should understand what God wants
and we can do so in one way above all
by studying everything that he is by
reasoning
we can exceed to redefine tunnel
perspective
Spinoza made a famous distinction
between two ways of looking at life
we can I the seed acoustically from our
limited point of view
as he put it sub specie jurists Eunice
under the aspect
time all we can look at things globally
and eternally
sub specie attorney Tartus under the
aspect of eternity
on nature means that will always be
divided between the two
Central Life pulls us toward time-bound
partial view
but our recent intelligence can give us
unique access to another perspective
it can quite literally allowance and
Hispanics have comes beautifully lyrical
to participate in a tunnel totality
normally we call back whatever is bad
for ass
and good whatever increases our power an
advantage but Espinosa
to be truly ethical means rising above
such local concerns
it might all sound for beating but
Spinoza envisage his philosophy
as a route to a life based on freedom
from guilt
from sorrow from PT or from shame
happiness involves lining all-wheel with
that of the universe
the universe gold as its own projects
and its our task
to understand rather than rail against
these
three-person is one conscious if the
necessities that compel a school
Spinoza rights the wise man the person
who understands how when why things
are possesses eternally true complacency
of spirit
needless to say these ideas cool Spinoza
into
very deep trouble he was excommunicated
from the Jewish community from saddam in
the rabbis issued a richness sure am
hence the philosopher it went by the
decree of the
angels and by the commander the holy man
we excommunicate expel curse
and damn hawked Espinosa with all the
classes which are written in the book at
all
cusick be here by day and cusick be here
by night custody he when he lies down
and custody he when he rises up Espinoza
was forced to flee Amsterdam
and eventually settled in the hague
where he lived quietly and peacefully as
a lens grinder
and private tutor to his death in 1677
spinners his work was lucky for gotten
down the ages
Hagel took an interest as it could
consign and several other twentieth
century philosophers
but from many perspectives Spinoza's
work constitutes cool warning
about failures a philosophy the ethics
is one of the world's most beautiful
books
it contains a calming perspective for
storing take on life
it replaces the Qatar superstition with
a wise and consoling pantheism
and yet Spinoza's work failed utterly to
convince any but a few
to abandon traditional religion and to
move towards a rationalist
why system of belief the reasons are no
way
simple and banal Spinoza fail to
understand
like so many philosophers before and
since that will lead people to religion
isn't just a reason
but far more importantly emotion belief
fear
tradition people stick with the police
because they like the ritual the
communal meals
the yearly traditions the beautiful
architecture to music and the lovely
language without and cynical court
church
Spinoza's ethics arguably contains a
whole lot more wisdom than the Bible
because it comes without any the Bible
supporting structure
it remains a marginal work studied here
and there
universities in the West what the
traditional religion
that Spinoza thought outmoded in the 16
seventies
continues to thrive and convince people
if we're
ever to replace traditional beliefs we
must remember just how much religion is
helped along
by ritual tradition art and a desire to
belong
all things that Spinoza despite its
great wisdom
ignored it is peril in his bold attempt
to replace the Bible